I've brought him.
（兵士53番）
連れてまいりました
Enter.
（ドルフ）入れ
ふん
Well, well, if it isn't King Albert.
これは これは アルベルト王
Dolph!
ドルフ
これは いったい
どういうつもりだ
Just what on earth do you intend by doing this?!
ふん
I thought we could enjoy a tasty meal together.
ぜひ ご一緒に おいしい
お食事をと思いましてね
How unfortunate.
残念ですが あなたの分は
予約が入ってないようです
It appears nothing was prepared for you.
Keep him restrained.
（ドルフ）押さえていろ
（兵士19番）はっ
（ドルフ）ふーん
So that's what you're after?!
やはり それが狙いか！
（ドルフ）フーフフッ
さあて―
Now, then, I suppose it is about time to end the game of hide-and-seek with the cute princess.
カワイイ姫君との かくれんぼも
そろそろ終わりにしましょう
King Albert.
アルベルト王
Or should I simply call you Albert?
いえ アルベルト
（ドルフ）フッハハハハハ
（スターラ姫の荒い息）
（兵士Ａ）見つかったか？
Have you found her?
No, no luck.
（兵士Ｂ）いやっ ダメだ
（兵士Ａ）俺は向こうを見てくる
I'll look over there.
Listen up, men!
（兵士隊長）いいか お前ら
目的はウッドキューブだ
Our objective is the Wood Cube!
Do not kill the princess yet!
姫は まだ殺すなよ！
（アルベルト王）
こんなことをして 許されると
思っているのか ドルフ
Do you think you'll be able to get away with this, Dolph?!
（ドルフ）
フッフッフッ　許される？
"Get away with this"?
Who will pass their judgement on me?
誰が私に
審判を下すというのです？
You have no allies left here, Albert.
ここには もう
あなたの味方はいないんだよ
アルベルト
This trip around the world that you planned...
（ドルフ）
あなたが計画した この地球旅行
It was the perfect opportunity for me.
私にとっては 最大の
チャンスだったのですよ
With the exception of you and the princess, everyone here is my subordinate.
王と姫以外 私の部下で
固められたのでね
But why?
なぜだ　なぜ裏切った ドルフ
Why did you betray me, Dolph?!
（ドルフ）ああ
人聞きが悪いな アルベルト
That's a mean thing to say, Albert.
I am thankful to you.
あなたには感謝していますよ
You raised me, an orphan,
孤児だった私を
ここまで育ててくれ―
and even made me the general of the kingdom!
王国の指揮官にまで
してくださってね
（アルベルト王）
うううっ だったら なぜだ？
Then why?!
Do you think I've been supporting you without any ambitions of my own?
私が何の野心も持たず
今まで支えていたとでも？
This is justified by the will of God, Albert.
これは 正当なる神の裁きですよ
アルベルト
Dolph-sama!
（兵士隊長）ドルフ様！
（ドルフ）うん？
We've found the princess!
（兵士隊長）
姫が見つかりました！
Okay!
オーケー！ すぐ行くっ
I'll be right there!
So, it's about time for you to think about your last words, King Albert.
…とまあ そういうわけで―
そろそろ辞世の句でも ひとつ
お願いしますよ アルベルト王
Traitor!
裏切り者めっ
What's wrong with you?!
（スターラ姫）何だよ お前ら
身分わきまえてんのかよ
Don't you know your place?!
Well, well, if it isn't Princess Starla.
（ドルフ）
これは これは スターラ姫
Good evening.
ご機嫌 麗しゅう
Dolph, you bastard!
（スターラ姫）ドルフ　てめえ
自分で何やってんのか
分かってんのか　コラーッ！
Do you have any idea what you're doing?!
Your words are always less refined than your looks.
相変わらず
お顔のわりに口が下品だ
Of course I know what I am doing.
もちろん分かっていますとも
After acquiring this Wood Cube from King Albert and that Wood Cube from you, Princess...
私はこの アルベルト王の
ウッドキューブと―
その 姫のウッドキューブを
手に入れ―
...I shall reactivate the ancient weapon.
古代兵器を
よみがえらせるんです
Yes... So that I may become the new king of Fay!
そう 私がフェイ王国の
新たな王となるためにね
ヒッハ　ここには
お前の仲間はいない
You have no allies here.
もう逃げられないんだよ
You can no longer escape.
Now, be a good girl and hand it over-
さあ おとなしく
それを渡すんだ
だあっ！　だあっ！
He... He's dead!
し… 死んでる
（兵士Ａ）ドルフ様
Princess! Hurray! Princess! Hurray!
（兵士６番）ひーめっ
（兵士11番たち）うあっ！
（兵士６番）
あそれっ ひーめっ
あそれっ ひーめっ あそれっ
（兵士４番･６番）ひーめっ
（兵士４番･６番）あそれっ
（兵士11番たち）ええっ？
（兵士４番･６番）
ひーめっ あそれっ
（兵士たち）ひーめっ
（兵士一同）あそれっ ひーめっ
（兵士一同）
あそれっ ひーめっ
You scum!
（スターラ姫）お前らっ！
（兵士一同）ああっ！
I'll have you pay me back with interest!
利子は高く付くぞっ！
All right.
よし！ 父上の所へ案内しろ
Lead me to my father.
（兵士８番）
んっ？ ウッドキューブ？
A Wood Cube?
The Princess should be holding onto it tightly.
姫は しっかり持ってたはずだし
But what if...
いやあ もしかすると
（兵士８番）ええっ？
Ehh-
ちょっ ちょええええっ！
Super-eeeh!
This... Can't I become king with this?!
これ 俺 王になれちゃうって
やつじゃないか？
あっ いや いやいや
待て待て 落ち着け
No.
Wait.
Calm down.
Take a minute to think about this.
とりあえず 一服だ
After twelve years as a soldier,
兵士生活12年
I've always thought I would just die a grunt.
俺は このまま―
死んでいくものだとばかり
思っていたが―
I can't believe I would have this kind of chance...
まさか こんなチャンスが
ハア
I should give up.
（兵士８番）やめよう
俺が王になったところで
It's not like I have any plans after becoming king.
何かプランが
あるわけでもないし
Despite having gathered both,
まして これが
２つそろったところで―
I have no idea how to call the ancient weapon.
古代兵器の呼び出し方も
分からんよ
Hot!
あちっ！
のわああ！
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）のああ！
Nichijou 27
Good morning.
おはようございます
Super
Jumbo
Country-wide
Drawing
Lottery
I did it! I did it! I did it! I did it! I did it!
（祐子）やった！ やった
やった やった やったあ
Mio-chan!
みおちゃん　宝くじ
３等10万円が当たったあ！
I won the third prize in the lottery for 100,000 yen!
No way!
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）ウソ！
ええっ ちょっと おごってよ
Really?
Get me something.
Ah, what should I do?
ああ どうしよう　何買おう
What should I buy?
家とか買っちゃおうかなあ
つって
Maybe a house or something?
Just kidding.
ゆっこ
Yukko.
This is from last year.
これ 去年のだ
Well, well, it's not like lottery tickets win that often.
そうそう 宝くじなんて
当たんないって
Present
It's okay, don't try to console me.
（祐子）いいの　慰めはやめて
Besides, it's your birthday today, isn't it?
それはそうと 今日ゆっこの
誕生日でしょ？ はい！
Here.
Eh? No way!
えっ？ ウソッ　プレゼント？
A present? Thanks!
ありがとう
Can I open it?
開けてもいい？
うん　つまんないもんだよ
たまたま家(うち)にあったやつだし
Go ahead.
It's nothing special.
Just something I had around the house.
That's fine.
いいって いいって
その気持ちが うれしいんだから
It's the thought that counts.
Octopus
Wasabi
Teacher's Lounge
Sakurai-sensei.
（高崎(たかさき)先生）桜井(さくらい)先生
Ah, Takasaki-sensei.
ああっ 高崎先生
おはようございます
Good morning.
（高崎）おはようございます
Sensei, can you do anything about that Aioi girl?
先生 相生のやつ
どうにか なりませんかね
That
Aioi
Girl
She's never handed in any homework.
一向に宿題を
やってこないのですが
Ah, I-I'm sorry.
うああ　すっ すいません
I'd be thankful if you could really take charge
and do something, as her homeroom teacher.
担任から こう―
ガツンと１発やっていただくと
ありがたいんですが
ええっ ああっ すいません
Ah, sorry.
I'll talk to Aioi-san about it.
相生さんには
伝えておきますので
W-Well, I had better get going for first period.
そ… それでは 私
１時限目 向かいますので
（高崎）よろしく頼みますよ
I'll leave it to you.
Excuse me.
（桜井）失礼します
（富岡(とみおか)先生）あっ！
（桜井）ああっ！
I'm sorry!
ああ すいません
Are you all right?
大丈夫ですか？
お茶かかりませんでしたか？
Did I get any tea on you?
（高崎）
ハアッ　守ってやりてえっ
Nichijou 28
I want to protect her!
For me, who has not had any luck with women for the past 26 years,
生まれて この方 26年
女というものに
全く縁がなかった私にとって―
Sakurai-sensei is like a bamboo shoot suddenly sprouting in the garden.
桜井先生は 庭先に
不意に生えたタケノコのようだ
Ah, no, no!
（高崎）いかん いかん
As a teacher, bringing feelings of love into the workplace is unacceptable!
教育者として 恋愛感情を
職場に持ち込むなど 言語道断
Get it together, Takasaki Manabu!
しっかりしろ！ 高崎学(まなぶ)
Oh, she forgot something.
（高崎）忘れ物
Sakurai-sensei!
（高崎）桜井先生！
You forgot your notebook.
“黒いの”忘れてますよ
（桜井）ああっ
すいません 高崎先生
Ah, thank you, Takasaki-sensei.
ああ でも 私の“黒いの”
これですので
But this is my notebook.
Takasaki-sensei!
（富岡）
高崎先生　私の“黒いの”
どこ持ってくんですか？
Where are you taking my notebook to?
ああっ すいません
I-I'm sorry.
（桜井）
ああ じゃあ 失礼します
Well, excuse me.
ハアアッ
I want to invite her to hunt shiitake mushrooms!
（高崎）
シイタケ狩りに誘いてえ
I wonder if Sakurai-sensei has a boyfriend at the moment.
桜井先生は 今
彼氏とかいるのだろうか？
She doesn't wear a ring, so it's hard to imagine she's married.
指輪をしていないところから
察すると―
結婚しているとは
考えがたいし
So I might actually have a chance?
果たして 私にも
チャンスはあるのだろうか？
I wonder what kind of music she likes? Animals? Sports? Edible wild plants?
好きな音楽は？ 好きな動物は？
好きなスポーツは？
好きな山菜は？
はっ！ 何考えてるんだ俺は！
What am I thinking about?!
How impure.
不純だ　不純だぞ 高崎学
How impure, Takasaki Manabu!
There is no way I can fulfil my responsibility of being a role model for the students like this!
こんなことじゃ
“生徒のかがみ”として―
立派に職務を全うできんぞ
Oh, Takasaki-sensei.
（校長）
おっ 高崎先生　生徒のことで
何か お悩みですかな？
Are you worrying over your students?
But wouldn't it be all right to at least ask what kind of food she likes?
（高崎）
しかし 好きな食べ物ぐらい
聞くのは いいんじゃないか？
What kind of food do you like, Sakurai-sensei?
桜井先生の好きな食べ物は
何ですか？
Um, I eat anything.
（桜井）
えっと 何でも食べますよ
Ha ha ha, is that so?
（高崎）
ハッハッハッ そうですか
シイタケなんか どうです？
How about shiitake mushrooms?
You can fry them, or even boil them.
焼いても 煮てもいけますし
Let's see.
（桜井）そうですねえ
揚げてもいいですか？
Is it all right to deep-fry them?
Of course.
（高崎）もちろん
揚げるのもオーケーです
It's also all right to deep-fry them.
Then, it's all right to deep-fry them?
（桜井）
揚げても いいですよねえ
All right! This can work!
（高崎）よっし いける！
自然にだ  自然にだぞ 高崎学
Naturally.
Do it naturally, Takasaki Manabu.
Talk to her naturally, like you're talking to an eggplant at home.
家(うち)のナスに話しかけているように
自然に話しかけるんだ
Sakurai-sensei.
（高崎）桜井先生
（桜井）あっ ああっ
はい　何でしょう？
Yes, what is it?
I'm sorry that I keep stopping you.
すいません
たびたび呼び止めてしまって
Do you have a boyfriend that you're going out with at the moment?
今 つきあっている彼氏は
いるんですか？
What am I saying?!
（高崎）
何 言ってんだ　俺はあっ
Am I an idiot?!
バカか？ 俺はバカなのか？
アホなのか？
Am I an idiot?!
A moron?!
（桜井）はい  いませんよ
No, I don't.
（桜井）
いませんよ いませんよ
I don't.
（高崎）ほっ ほっ ほっ
ほいきたああ！
Yahoo!
（桜井）
あ… あの 高崎先生？
U-Um, Takasaki-sensei.
（高崎）
ほっ！ ああ いやっ
失礼なことを聞いてしまって
Ah, sorry.
I asked something impolite.
It turned out all right.
（高崎）結果オーライだっ
Sakurai-sensei, do your best in first period.
桜井先生
１時限目 頑張ってください
Okay.
はいっ 高崎先生も
頑張ってくださいね
You do your best, too, Takasaki-sensei.
Okay.
はいっ！
Well, excuse me.
じゃっ すいません
失礼しまーす
I'll be off.
You do your best, too, Takasaki-sensei.
（桜井）
高崎先生も頑張ってくださいね
You do your best, too, Takasaki-sensei.
（高崎）うおお
フンッ フンッ フンッ
Ah, I see you're working hard.
おお 精が出ますな
Wait!
（死神）ちょっと あの
鎌 返してくださーい
Um... Please give back my scythe!
I need to pawn this scythe in order to buy food, or else I'm going to die!
（天狗(てんぐ)）この鎌を質に入れて
食べ物を買わないと死んでしまう
ハアッ ハアッ　しまった 川だ
Oh, no! It's a river!
I did it.
（天狗）やったあ
（死神）
ううっ 返してくださーい
Please give it back!
（天狗）あっちゃー
First comes rock, next comes paper, rockscispaper doesn't count,
（はかせ･なの）
♪ 最初はグー その次パー
rock, paper, scissors!
Yay, I won!
うわあっ 勝ったあ
（なの）ああ わああっ
Thanks!
ありがとう
（リモコンを押した音）
（はかせ）えいっ
This isn't all of it!
（通販の司会者）
これだけではありません
（はかせ）えいっ
（ＣＭの女性）ナタデココ入り
I hear a voice in-
Tomorrow's weather is going to be-
（はかせ）えいっ
（気象予報士）あしたからの天気は
（はかせ）えーいっ
（アニメの声優）ミラクルピーンチ
Miraculous Beach!
This is where it all begins!
（アニメの声優）
ここからが見せどころよ
Mind
Right now, I'm gonna try to say something that isn't going through your head at all, Mio-chan.
今 みおちゃんの頭の中で―
全く思ってもないこと
言ってみよっか？
What, what?
“すちゃらかＯＬ旅日記”
An Inconsistent Office Lady's Journey Diary.
ちょっと
It was, a little bit.
（祐子）くううっ
Jumping onto a train at the last
second is dangerous.
Mio-chan, Mai-chan, the train's already here!
（祐子）
みおちゃん　麻衣ちゃん
もう電車来てるよ　急いで
Hurry up!
Wait up!
I made it! I'm safe!
（祐子）
よいしょっ　なんとか セーフ！
（みお）プププ
１人で間に合ってる
You're the only one that made it.
（水上麻衣(みなかみまい)）プププ
Selemat tinggal!
TL note: Indonesian for "Farewell".
スラマッ ティンガル
What should we have?
Well, bring on the orders.
（板前）
さあ どんどん
おっしゃってよ
I'll take one pitoro.
TL note: Pitoro is an exquisite part of the pig which is usually rich with fat.
（客Ａ）ビントロを１つ
I'll take an Amberjack, no, a Hamachi!
（客Ｂ）ブリ　いや ハマチ
（板前）どんどん おっしゃってよ
Well, bring on the orders.
Can I have some tuna and some halibut, please?
マグロとエンガワください
One sea urchin, please.
ウニ１つ
Let's see.
ええ ビントロ１つと―
One pitoro and...
プッ　忘れちゃった
I forgot.
He forgot!
（祐子･みお）
わーすれちゃったーよー
Nichijou 29
（長野原(ながのはら)よしの）あっ？
あっ こんにちは
Ah, hello.
（なの）
あっ えっ？ こ… こんにちは
あの 何でしょうか？
Uh, hello.
Um, do you need something?
いやあ　あっ？ ああ
Well...
Hey! What are you trying to do?
ちょっと ちょっと
さっきから
何なんでしょうか？
いやあ 変わってて
面白いなあって
Well, I thought it was strange and interesting.
I-It's not strange!
かか… 変わってなんかいませんよ
普通ですし
ネジだってアクセサリーですし
It's normal!
A key can be an accessory!
どああ！
Hey, hey, how did you do that?
（よしの）ねえねえ
これ どうやってやったの？
ねえねえ お姉さんに教えて
Hey, hey, tell me about it.
Please give it back!
（なの）
返してください 返してください
Come on. Just tell me how you did that.
Please give it back!
All right, then. Let's do this.
よしっ じゃあ
こうしよう　フンッ
Bye.
（なの）なんで？
Why?!
（なの）ううう
（よしの）ごめん ごめん
Sorry, sorry.
It was just a joke.
冗談 冗談
Don't joke!
冗談じゃないですよ
返してくださいよ
Please give it back!
どっちだ
Which hand is it?
（なの）かばんです！
It's in the bag!
Wow, correct!
わっ 正解！ じゃあ 第２問！
Now, question two.
Kenta-kun's mother bought ten apples.
ケンタ君のお母さんが
リンゴを10個買ってきました
そのうち３個
お母さんが食べました
Of those, his mother ate three.
She gave four of the remaining apples to Yumiko, the neighbour.
残りのうち４個を
隣のユミコちゃんにあげました
Where is your hand?
あなたの手首は どこでしょう？
In your bag!
かばんです！
Amazing!
すごーい　またまた大正解
You got it correct again!
Then please hurry up and give it back!
じゃあ 早く返してください
Now, then. The final question.
それでは最後の問題です
If you get this correct, you win a hand!
（よしの）
これに正解するとなんと
手首がもらえます
ええっ？
もともと私のなのに
But it was mine to begin with!
Do you not want the hand?
手首が欲しくないか！
I want it!
欲しいでーす
Then, here is the question.
じゃあ 問題
Say "kaban" ten times.
TL note: "Kaban" means bag.
〝かばん かばん〞と
10回言ってください
Bag Bag Bag Bag Bag Bag Bag Bag Bag Bag.
かばん かばん かばん
かばん かばん
かばん かばん！
絵を描くときに下に置くのは？
What do you draw on?
Ba- I mean a drawing board!
TL note: "Gaban" is a drawing board.
かばっ じゃなくて
画板ですっ
ブッブーッ
The correct answer was paper.
TL note: "Kami" is paper.
正解は紙でした
No way!
そんなあ ズルいです
That's not fair!
（よしの）
ウフフフッ　冗談よ 冗談
I'm just joking.
Please don't hang around me!
もうっ 私に
付きまとわないでください！
All right, all right.
分かった 分かった　ごめんね
I'm sorry.
（よしの）イヒヒッ
（よしの）
あっ！ 取れちゃった
Oh, it came off.
わあっ ひゃああ！
It came off!
（なの）取れたあ  取れたあ
取れたあ
It came off!
Mio!
（よしの）みお
（みお）うん？
一緒 帰ろう
Let's go home together.
Huh?
あれっ お姉　大学帰り？
Onee, are you on the way home from university?
（よしの）いやあ　さっき
面白い人と会っちゃったよ
Man, I met a really interesting person earlier.
（みお）どんな人？
What kind of person?
Her arm came off.
（よしの）腕が取れてね
（みお）えっ？
What?
Also, she had a key attached.
（よしの）ネジが付いててね
What's with that?
（みお）何？ それ
There was a person like that.
（よしの）そんな人がいたんだよ
Really?
（みお）ええ 変なの
That's strange.
Word Of The Day
I want to act in a way that makes people think,
"Oh, that's pretty cool."
Nano, here I go!
なの　行くよ
Nichijou 30
All right!
はあーい
Magic ball.
（はかせ）魔球
Well, she's only a child, after all.
（阪本(さかもと)）まあ
ガキだしな　こんなもんか
About what you'd expect.
I won!
（はかせ）勝ったあ
負けました
I lost!
（阪本）なんだ こいつら
全然 なっとらんじゃないか
What's up with these two?
They aren't even doing it properly...
Sakamoto, how many points did I just get?
阪本　はかせ 今の何点？
What!?
（阪本）なにっ？
All right!
じゃあ はかせ いきますよ
Here it comes, Professor!
All right!
（はかせ）はーい　ほいっ
She hasn't even thrown it yet!
（阪本）まだ 投げてないのに？
（なの）ふんっ！
こ… こここ… 殺す気か？
I-Is she trying to kill me?!
Sakamoto-san, how many points did I just get?
阪本さーん
私 今の何点ですかあ？
You, too?!
（阪本）お前もか！
（はかせ）きゃあ
She swung again?!
（阪本）また 振りおった
You're next.
次 はい　阪本
Here, Sakamoto.
（阪本）なんで俺が？
っていうか―
Why me?
More importantly, how can I even hold a bat with hands like these?
この手でバット
持てるわけないだろ
Honestly... I mean, what do you think my hands are?
（阪本）まったく
大体 俺の手を
なんだと思ってるんだ
You even thoroughly examined the pads when I first arrived.
肉球をさんざん
プニプニしているくせに
これだからガキは
This is why I can't stand kids...
ていっ てっ
Moe~
（なの･はかせ）ほええ
Well, you know.
（阪本）まあ あれだ
Just the two of you alone are kind of dangerous, so I'm watching.
お前たちだけだと危ないから
俺が見てやってんだ
I have no intention of participating.
俺は参加するつもりはない
Why don't you just play catch?
最初のうちはキャッチボールで
いいんじゃないか？
All right.
（なの）はいっ！
（はかせ）はいっ 監督
All right, Coach.
Coach?
（阪本）監督？
監督  グローブが
１個しかありません
Coach, we only have one glove!
You should be fine with your bare hands.
（阪本）
お前は 素手で大丈夫だろう
Coach, the glove doesn't fit very well.
監督　グローブが
ウマく入りません
It was perfectly fine on your other hand!
（阪本）
さっきは左手にしてただろう
Coach!
（なの）監督
（はかせ）監督
（阪本）クウーッ
しょうがない やつらだなあ
You guys are helpless.
Professor!
（なの）はかせ　いきますよ
Here it comes!
Bring it on!
バチコーイ
（なの）うーん　えいっ！
Ah, man.
（なの）ああ もう
どこいっちゃったんだろう
Where did it go?
（祐子）それでねえ
先生に怒られちゃってさあ
And then the teacher got mad at me.
Well, of course he would, you know.
（みお）
やっぱり そうなるよねえ
I agree.
（麻衣）同感
You think so, too, Mai-chan?
麻衣ちゃんも そう思う？
But he didn't have to get that mad.
I guess, but you'd better watch out from now on.
（みお）
だよね　でも これからは
気をつけないとね
Yeah, you never know what will happen.
Ah, thank you.
（なの）あっ すいません
Oh! Gentleman!
（ナレーター）Oh(オウ)！ Gentleman(ジェントルマン)！
So yeah, Mai-chan, can you lend me again?
（祐子）
でさあ 相談なんだけど
麻衣ちゃん また貸してね
All right.
（麻衣）いいよ
Hooray! You really do gotta have friends, after all.
I wonder if that's the person sis was talking about.
（みお）
お姉が言ってた子かな？
（祐子）
持つべきものは友人だよね
いやあ 助かりますな
Man, you're a saviour.
Birthday Present
（祐子）
くうっ ううっ にっ
うくくっ
くうっ くくくっ くうっ
ヒッ ううっ ハア
うっ うくくっ がっ
うんが！
I am the Wood Cube.
Whoever possesses me can acquire the ancient weapon.
Well, then, the next episode of Nichijou is episode 8.
Narration:    Wakamoto Norio
Look forward to it!
（ウッドキューブ）
私はウッドキューブ
私の あるじになれば―
古代兵器を手に入れることが
できちゃう　ハッハッハッ
さて次回の「日常」は
第８話　お楽しみに